Rodney Gilbert Papers
Rodney Gilbert Papers
1910-1968
Gilbert, Rodney, 1889-
6 linear ft.
American journalist, Far East expert. Collection includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, published material, notebooks, artifacts and other material.
2746524
Biographical History
Rodney Gilbert (1889-1968) was an American conservative editorial writer and newspaper columnist.
Born in Lancaster, Pennsylvania, Gilbert graduated from Franklin and Marshall College. In 1912 Gilbert went to China to travel the country; he began as a salesman for Dr. Williams' Pink Pills for Pale People but ended up spending 17 years there, becoming fluent in Chinese and eventually working as a correspondent for the North China Daily News. In 1926 his series of columns on traveling in Chinese Turkestan were compiled into his first book, What's Wrong With China. He was a strong supporter of Chinese nationalism and of Chiang Kai-Shek, and firmly anti-Communist.
In 1929 he joined the staff of the Herald Tribune as an editorial writer and returned to the United States. His editorials, which were largely conservative and anti-Communist in nature and which were published under the pseudonym "Heptisax," appeared regularly for 15 years, until 1944. From 1944 to 1946 Gilbert served as Dean of the Post-Graduate School of Journalism of the Central Political Institute of Chungking, organized and established under the auspices of Columbia University. Later, he collaborated with Columbia University to bring Chinese journalism students to the United States to study.
In addition to his Heptisax column, articles and book reviews under his own byline frequently appeared in the Herald Tribune and, later, in conservative-leaning magazines such American Legion and National Review.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Rodney Gilbert Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, memorabilia, photographs, propaganda and writings.
Biographical material consists of a semi-humorous curriculum vitae by Gilbert of his activities to 1953.
Correspondence spans more than fifty years, and includes both incoming and outgoing items. The earliest correspondence is to his friend Francis Lyman Windolph, and consists of numerous long letters detailing his experiences during his first years in China (1912-1916). Notable correspondents include Madame Chiang Kai-Shek, OSS director William J. "Wild Bill" Donovan, Chinese ambassador Hollington Tong, Nancy Yu (Yu Meng-Yen), founder and editor of Taiwan's English-language newspaper The China Post, Commissioner of Narcotics H. J. Anslinger, and the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), for whom Gilbert engaged in anti-Japanese propaganda work. There is also correspondence with various publishers and editors, including Alfred Knopf, E. P. Dutton & Co., Ray Henle (Three Star Extra), Eugene Lyons (Readers Digest), and Frederic Nelson (Saturday Evening Post). Several folders of material relate to Gilbert's work with Columbia University: as lecturer, as Dean of the Post-Graduate School of Journalism of the Central Political Institute of Chungking (a Columbia University project), and with regards to a project to bring Chinese journalism students to the United States to study.
Memorabilia is a mixture of personal items and items collected by Gilbert as souvenirs. Personal items include a date book, clippings about Gilbert, a flag signed with Chinese characters (possibly by his students in Chungking), and various legal documents (alien registration card, military cards, press card, etc.). Of particular interest is a sheet of paper in an unidentified script which, according to an accompanying note, is a tribal safe-conduct letter for Gilbert during his travels in Mongolia. Souvenirs include maps, a Chungking city directory, clippings and typescripts of articles by other journalists such as Dorothy Thompson, and a dozen or so very nice examples of black-and-white block-printed Chinese paper, some with highly detailed designs.
The collection contains a large number of Photographs, some in albums and others loose. Many of the photographs in albums have captions, and a few of the loose photographs are captioned on the back. Photographs include people, places, buildings, landscapes and so on from China, Taiwan and Mongolia. The vast majority are candid shots, presumably taken by Gilbert, but there are also some official photographs from the Chinese Ministry of Information. In some cases, the photographs were in a labeled or addressed envelope; these items have been kept together so as to retain the original organization.
Propaganda consists of both printed/published items as well as "messages" designed (and in some cases illustrated) by Gilbert, with sketches and typed drafts. The majority is anti-Japanese in nature, having been done during World War II, but there is also some anti-Communist propaganda from the 1950s.
Writings contains a wide range of pieces by Gilbert, the majority of which center around his expertise in Asia generally and China specifically; two prevalent topics are the threat of Communism and the danger of narcotics. This series consists of articles for various newspapers and magazines; book reviews written for the Herald Tribune; a book manuscript; more than 15 years of weekly editorials written for the Herald Tribune; columns written for the same paper under the pseudonym "Heptisax"; Gilbert's personal journals from China; letters to the editor, both as himself and as "Heptisax"; speeches; and assorted miscellaneous notes and drafts.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender and, within that, chronologically. Other material is arranged alphabetically by type or title, where possible. Editorials and Heptisax columns are arranged chronologically.
Separated Material
Several of Gilbert's books have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these titles. A list of these titles is provided in the collection (see Writings: Books: Miscellaneous below).
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Military history; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973.; Chennault, Claire Lee, 1893-1958.; Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1897-2003.; Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959.; Elliston, Herbert Berridge.; FitzGerald, Desmond, 1888-1947.; Gilbert, Rodney, 1889-; Heptisax.; Hornbeck, Stanley Kuhl, 1883-1966.; Kao, George, 1912-2008.; Tong, Hollington Kong, 1887-1971.; Windolph, F. Lyman (Francis Lyman), 1889-1978.; New York herald tribune.; United States. -- Office of Strategic Services.; Journalism -- China.; Journalism -- Taiwan.; Journalism -- China -- History.; Journalists -- United States.; Propaganda.; Psychological warfare -- China.; Psychological warfare -- Japan.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda.; China -- Foreign relations.; China -- Politics and government -- 1912-1949.; China -- Travel and description.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. H. M. Gilbert, 1968.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Autobiographical sketch, by Gilbert, to 1953 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Alfred A. Knopf, 1944 (Box 1)
  - American Council, Institute of Pacific Relations, 1938; confidential report for those attending conference on "Problems of American Far East Policy," Princeton, New Jersey (Box 1)
  - American Mercury (Box 1)
  - Anslinger, H. J. (Harry J.), 1942; 1954-1962; commissioner of narcotics; includes some printed items by Anslinger (Box 1)
  - Asia (magazine), 1931; includes several photographs and clippings, annotated by Gilbert, used for an article in the May 31, 1931 issue (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Articles: Asia (magazine).
  - Blair, C. Ledyard, 1943; includes a number of clippings by Leo Wolman (Box 1)
  - Cahn, Julius, 1954; includes memo on a meeting of the U.S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee on International Opium Protocol (Box 1)
  - Chennault, Claire, 1945; regarding the "indoctrination and training of graduates from the Chungking School of Journalism" (Box 1)
  - Chiang Kai-Shek, Madame, 1950; 1955-1957; long chatty letters to Gilbert; printed copy of an "Easter Meditation" (Box 1)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1944-1949 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University
    - Correspondence, 1943-1959 (Box 1)
    - Printed material, 1943; 1945,; undated; includes Columbia University Press catalog (1943), a report from the Dean on the Chinese Post-Graduate School of Journalism in Chungking, and a copy of the loyalty oath required of all university professors (Box 1)
    - Student work, copies of papers written by students, presumably as assignments for a journalism course (Box 1)
    - "Students - Chungking", originally in an envelope with this label hand-written on it; includes correspondence with Dean Ackerman, faculty at other universities, and the students themselves (Box 1)
      See also Kao, George; Yu, Nancy
    - Miscellany (Box 1)
  - Conley, Tom, 1953-1955 (Box 1)
  - Davis, R. W., 1935; 1941 (Box 1)
  - Donovan, William J., 1948; 1953 (Box 1)
  - E. P. Dutton & Co., Inc., 1956 (Box 1)
  - Elliston, Herbert, 1956; includes several clippings of articles by Elliston (Box 1)
  - Epstein, Julius, 1953; mentions Gilbert's assistance to "me and the Katyn Committee, back in 1949" (Box 1)
  - Explorers Club, 1942; regarding something called tsamba (Box 1)
  - Fitzgerald, Desmond, 1954; includes letter to Fitzgerald from Hollington Tong, regarding "the character of a race" (Box 1)
  - Forum (magazine), 1931; relates to Gilbert's article, "Motormania" (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Articles: Forum (magazine) for copy of article
  - Fraser, David, 1943; includes clipping of letter to the editor from Fraser, on Marshal Badoglio in Italy (Box 1)
  - Gilbert, C. V. (Mrs.) (mother), 1911
  - Gilbert, Hilda Murray (wife?), undated (Box 1)
  - Hall, Charlie, 1954; 1957 (Box 1)
  - Henle, Ray, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Heptisax reader mail, 1938-1944; 1948,; 1959,; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Heptisax columns: Reader responses for published responses to Heptisax columns.
  - Herald Tribune, 1938-1944; 1956,; 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1943; 1957 (Box 2)
  - Hornbeck, Stanley, 1943-1944; 1956,; 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Hsia, C. L., 1944; 1946; with China News Service (Box 2)
  - Hunt, Betty Knowles, 1947; 1956 (Box 2)
  - Hutton, E. F., 1947; typescript of speech given by Hutton before the Long Island Association (Box 2)
  - K---, Ralph J., 1956 (Box 2)
  - Kao, George, 1943; 1947; includes transcript of article, "The Mikado Must Go" (Box 2)
  - Kohlberg, Alfred, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Loeb, William, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Lyons, Eugene, 1947; 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - MacAlarney, Robert Emmet, 1944; undated (Box 2)
  - Manchester Union Leader, See Loeb, William.
  - Munson, Lyle H., 1950-1959; undated; includes numerous clippings without a byline, some of which may be by Gilbert (Box 2)
    See also Writings: Articles: "For Lyle".
  - Murray, Gladstone, 1948; includes "copies of three memoranda which I have prepared" on propaganda (Box 2)
  - Murray, John, 1938-1939; bank drafts (Box 2)
  - Myers, W. D. ("Dick"), 1955 (Box 2)
  - "N. C. N.", 1956; only the writer's initials are given; an "N.C.N." is also mentioned in a few other letters (Box 2)
  - National Review, 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - Nelson, Frederic, 1947; 1953,; 1954,; 1957 (Box 2)
  - North, Maxine (Mrs. Robert Guilford North), 1958 (Box 2)
  - OSS (Office of Strategic Services), 1944-1948 (Box 2)
  - Paterson, Isabel, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Pratt, F. L., 1943 (Box 2)
  - Pyne, H. Rivington, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Raman, T. E., 1943 (Box 2)
  - Reader's Digest, See Lyons, Eugene.
  - Remington, W. E. (Woodbern Edwin), 1941; regarding his book, Cross Winds of Empire (Box 2)
  - Saturday Evening Post, See Nelson, Frederic.
  - Simkins, Willard, 1944; 1957 (Box 2)
  - Smith, H. Alexander, 1950; 1957 (Box 2)
  - Socialist Labor Party, 1949; includes printed pamphlet, "Socialist Labor Party and the War" (Box 2)
  - Sokolsky, George, 1944; includes two clippings of columns by Sokolsky (Box 2)
  - Soong Mei-ling, See Chiang Kai-Shek, Madame.
  - Syngman Rhee, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Tan, Alfred, undated (Box 2)
  - Three Star Extra, See Henle, Ray.
  - Tong, Hollington, 1946; 1954-1957; Chinese ambassador; includes clipping of column by Herbert Elliston (Box 2)
    See also Fitzgerald, Desmond.
  - Tooker, John C., 1946 (Box 2)
  - Tsiang Tingfu, 1950; 1955 (Box 2)
  - Tseng H. P., 1946-1947; 1950 (Box 2)
  - Vaillancourt, Emile, 1943-1944; includes copy of "Canada's Mission in a Free World," an address to the Kiwanis Club of Ottawa (Box 2)
  - W. H. Donald Scholarship, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Wang Chi-Chen, 1939; 1943-1944,; 1949,; 1963; includes reprint of monograph, "Lusin: A Chronological Record" by Wang (Box 2)
  - Wei, Jimmy, 1955; 1957,; undated (Box 2)
  - Weisshart, Herb ("Bosco"), 1955; 1957 (Box 2)
  - William, Maurice, 1936-1942; includes carbon copies of letters from William to others, as well as typed transcriptions of news clippings, speeches etc. by Walter Lippman and others (Box 2)
  - Willkie, Wendell, undated; 4-page letter from Gilbert to Willkie on political matters (Box 2)
  - Windolph, F. Lyman, 1912-1916; 1922,; 1929,; 1956,; 1968; last item is a letter from Windolph to Gilbert's widow, indicating that he is sending her the other letters (Box 3)
  - Winslow, Alan, undated (Box 3)
  - Wolman, Leo, See Blair, C. Ledyard.
  - Yeh, George K. C., 1960-1961; on Chinese Embassy letterhead (Box 3)
  - Yu, Nancy (Yu Meng-Yen), 1945-1946; editor of China Post; includes lengthy letters from Gilbert about his activities (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z (Box 3)
  - Unidentified, from Gilbert, 1944; 1948,; 1955-1956,; 1958,; undated (Box 3)
  - Unidentified, to Gilbert, 1940; 1947,; 1954,; undated; includes 4-page handwritten unsigned note which may be from Gilbert, and a 3-page letter in beautiful Chinese calligraphy (Box 3)
  - Envelopes
- Memorabilia
  - Calendar / date book, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Chinese papers, numerous examples of block-printed Chinese paper, varying sizes, all in black and white, some very complex designs (Oversize 1)
  - Chungking Reporter, 1944-1945; 5 issues, including one with headline about Japanese surrender (Oversize 2)
  - Clippings about Gilbert, 1936; 1938,; 1943,; 1946,; 1956,; 1961; includes announcements of his posting to China, reviews of his books, etc. (Box 3)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous, 1936-1966; press releases from China New Service; part of a Christmas address by Chiang Kai-Shek; clippings of columns by Damon Runyon, Dorothy Thompson, others; an annotated cartoon; miscellaneous other items (Box 3)
  - Flag, Chinese flag, with handwritten Chinese characters on star (Box 3)
  - Legal documents, 1944; 1950,; undated; alien registration card, military passes, travel passes, etc. (Box 3)
  - Maps, in Chinese, Japanese and English (Oversize 2)
  - Safe-conduct letter, 1913; according to accompanying documentation, the first lines translate as "business at the office of the Horde" and the document was "written by Makhsut Padshah...Imperial Prince of Hanni, to the Chonglari, meaning the great ones of [the] mountain communities northeast of Hanni...recommending Rodney Gilbert to their care"; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, Chungking city directory; coin; blank certificate of service in the war against Japan; handwritten Chinese characters; etc. (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Album (1), [1916?]; cover says "Tabul 1916" but it is not certain this is correct; faded photos of people, places, animals; most have penciled captions, many of which include the appellation "Mongol" (Box 4)
  - Album (2), 1912-1913; color photos of buildings, people, places in China; some have captions (Box 4)
  - Album (3), undated; black and white photos, most of buildings but some of soldiers; no captions
  - Album (4), Oct 1916; very faded black and white photos, most of landscapes, buildings, etc.; no captions
  - "Mr. Donald...", undated; several photos with accompanying note (Box 4)
  - "To Mrs. C. V. Gilbert", [1913?]; group photo with long, detailed inscription on back (Box 4)
  - "From Mrs. Sao-Ke Alfred Sze", undated; black and white photos, various sizes, some with captions; originally in an envelope addressed to Gilbert (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, black and white photos found loose in boxes; mostly candid shots with a few official photos stamped on the back "Ministry of Information, Republic of China"; a few have captions but most do not (Box 4)
    See also Correspondence: Asia (magazine) for original photos used in article published therein
- Propaganda
  - 21 Points of the Third International [Congress of Communist International], Moscow, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Messages developed, typescripts, printed material, notes, etc. of propaganda items developed by Gilbert (Box 5)
  - Published material, postcards; booklet, "Illustrated History of Sino-Russian Relations"; booklet, "The Great Swindle" (annotated by Gilbert); booklet, "Selection of Chinese Communist Posters and Comic Books"; sheet music, "The Guerrilla Marching Song"; etc. (Box 5)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "A Traveler in China's Wild Northwest", undated; scrapbook of articles about Gilbert's travels; apparently published in serial form over several months (Box 5)
    - American Legion (magazine), 1954-1955; 1962-1963; Dope; What You Should Know About Red China; The Price We Pay for Dope; Vice, Crime and Marijuana (Box 5)
    - American Mercury (magazine), Dec 1954; We Have a Law Against Russian Imports (Box 5)
    - Asia (magazine), 1931-1933; Amends to the Camel; China's Shadow Land; Bedlam in Shanghai; Japan Goes into Reverse Against Russia; In the Saddles of the Huns (Box 5)
      See also Correspondence: Asia (magazine) for letter and original photos
    - Chicago Sunday Tribune (newspaper), circa 1910; articles on Anna Strunsky, Maria-Teresa of Saxony, Virginia Brooks, and "Lands that have sunk beneath the sea" (Oversize 2)
    - China Post (newspaper), 1957; 1961,; undated (Box 5)
    - Christian Science Monitor, See "Monitor".
    - Cunarder (magazine), Mar 1931; Dining Out in China (Box 5)
    - Forum (magazine), May 1931; Motormania (Box 5)
      See also Correspondence: Forum for reader responses.
    - The Freeman (magazine), Nov 1950; Plan for Counter-Action (Box 5)
    - Herald Tribune (newspaper), 1951; 1953,; 1961,; 1963; articles written after Gilbert was no longer on the editorial staff (Box 5)
    - Liberty (magazine), Jan 1931; The Fragrant Worm (fiction) (Box 5)
    - Literary Digest (magazine), Nov 1933; Dope Traffic: Eastward Bound (Box 5)
    - "for Lyle", 1965-1966; possibly for Lyle Munson's news sheet (Box 6)
      See Correspondence: Munson, Lyle.
    - Manchester Union Leader (newspaper), 1966 (Box 6)
    - "Monitor" (magazine), [1945?]; typescripts of columns, with "Monitor" and date written on back; probably Christian Science Monitor (Box 6)
    - National Review (magazine), 1957-1959; 1961; numerous articles, all related to China and Communism (Box 6)
    - Reader's Digest (magazine), 1951 Apr-Jun; unidentified; articles on China and Communism, reprinted in numerous international editions (French, Swiss, Danish, German, Italian, Swedish, etc.); 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Saturday Evening Post (magazine), 1954-1955; articles on China and drugs (Box 6)
    - Worker's Magazine (newspaper), 1911; two articles about "Pipe McGraw", one about employers (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, unidentified publications (Box 6)
  - Book reviews
    - Herald Tribune, 1932-1944; 1947,; 1957; nearly all on books about China or Asia (Box 6)
  - Books
    - We the Editor, typescript for a book (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, list of titles transferred to Rare Books for cataloging (Box 7)
  - Editorials, Herald Tribune
    - Clippings, 1929-1946; loose clippings; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Notes, handwritten drafts of columns (Box 7)
    - Reader responses, 1943; 1945; published reader responses, including letters from Pearl Buck and Earl Browder (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, 1931; assorted clippings, mostly duplicates of the loose clippings above (Box 7)
  - Heptisax columns
    See also Letters to the Editor: As Heptisax.
    - Clippings, 1933-1944 (Box 7)
    - Clippings, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Reader responses, 1934; 1937-1944,; 1953; published reader responses
      See also Correspondence: Heptisax reader mail for letters sent directly to Gilbert.
  - Journals
    - Unidentified, 1912; handwritten journal of travels (Box 8)
    - "Peking Aug 15/16" (Box 8)
    - "Peking", 1918 (Box 8)
    - "Peking", 1921, Jan-Feb (Box 8)
  - Letters to the editor
    - as Gilbert, 1945; regarding General Pat Hurley's "eruption into print" (Box 8)
    - as Heptisax, 1935-1939 (Box 8)
  - Speeches
    - to National Press Club, undated; on Taiwan's place in the world (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Drafts, typescripts, fragments, etc., topics include words, travels in Germany, modern history, capitalism in China, etc. (Box 8)
    - Notes on the Chinese language, words, phrases, letters, etc.; evidently created as aid to learning Chinese (Box 8)
    - Notes on language development, possibly intended as an article or essay? (Box 8)